<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The B A C bothe in latyn and in Englysshe</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1538</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 14 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08694</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110843</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846311</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846311</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11271</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08694)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11271)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 82:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The B A C bothe in latyn and in Englysshe</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In Paules Chyrche yarde at the sygne of the maydens heed by thomas Petyt,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at Londo[n] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1538]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon; publication date suggested by STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Emmanuel College (University of Cambridge) Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Primers (Prayer-books) --  Church of England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="alphabet">
            <pb facs="tcp:11271:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11271:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> bothe in <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and in <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </head>
            <p>A a b c d e f g h j k l m n o p q r r ſ s t v u x y z &amp; r eſt Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_vowel_and_consonant_combinations">
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">e</cell>
                     <cell role="label">i</cell>
                     <cell role="label">o</cell>
                     <cell role="label">u</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>eb</cell>
                     <cell>ib</cell>
                     <cell>ob</cell>
                     <cell>ub</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>ec</cell>
                     <cell>ic</cell>
                     <cell>oc</cell>
                     <cell>uc</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>ed</cell>
                     <cell>id</cell>
                     <cell>od</cell>
                     <cell>ud</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>ef</cell>
                     <cell>if</cell>
                     <cell>of</cell>
                     <cell>uf</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>eg</cell>
                     <cell>ig</cell>
                     <cell>og</cell>
                     <cell>ug</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>be</cell>
                     <cell>bi</cell>
                     <cell>bo</cell>
                     <cell>bu</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>ce</cell>
                     <cell>ci</cell>
                     <cell>co</cell>
                     <cell>cu</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>de</cell>
                     <cell>di</cell>
                     <cell>do</cell>
                     <cell>du</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>fe</cell>
                     <cell>fi</cell>
                     <cell>fo</cell>
                     <cell>fu</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>ge</cell>
                     <cell>gi</cell>
                     <cell>go</cell>
                     <cell>gu</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="collection_of_prayers">
            <div type="Sign_of_the_Cross">
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n nomine patris &amp; filij &amp; ſpiritus ſancti. Amen. In the name of the Father and of the Sone and of the holy ghoſt. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Pater_Noster">
               <div xml:lang="lat" type="version">
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">
                        <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </seg>Ater noſter qui es in celis ſanctificetur nomen tuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Aduemat regnum tuum Fiat voluntas tua ſicut in celo et in terra. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>anem noſtrum quotidianum da nobis hodie. Et dimitte nobis debita noſtra / ſicut et
<pb facs="tcp:11271:2"/>nos dimittimꝰ debitoribus noſtris. Et ne nos inducas in temptacione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Sed libera nos a malo. Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="eng" type="version">
                  <p>OUr father which art in heuen halowed be thy name Let thi kyngdome come to vs. Thy wyl be fulfylled as well in earth / as it is in heuen. Gyue vs this day our dayly fode. And forgyue vs our offences / as we forgyue them that offend vs. And let vs not be ouercom by te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pta cyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. but deliuer vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all euell. Am<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="Ave_Maria">
               <div xml:lang="lat" type="version">
                  <p>AVe maria gratia plena dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s tecu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Benedicta tu in mulieribꝰ / et be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nedictus fructus ventris tui Jeſus.</p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="eng" type="version">
                  <p>HAyle Mary full of grace / our lorde is with the / blyſſed arte thou amonge all wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / &amp; bliſſed is the fruyte of thy wombe Jeſus Am<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="Apostles_Creed">
               <div xml:lang="lat" type="version">
                  <p>CRedo in deu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> patrem omnipo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tentem creatorem celi et terre
<pb facs="tcp:11271:2"/>Et in Jeſum chriſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> filiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eius vnicu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dominu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> noſtru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Qui co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceptus eſt de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſpirituſancto natꝰ ex maria virgine Paſſus ſub poncio pilato: crucifixus mortuus &amp; ſepultus. Deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dit ad in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ferna / tertia die reſurrexit a mortuis Aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dit ad celos ſedet ad dexteram dei patris omnipotentis. Inde ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turus eſt iudicare viuos et mortuos <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>redo in ſpiritum ſanctu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / ſanctam eccleſiam catholica<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / ſancto<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abrum"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>rum</ex>
                     </expan> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>muni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>onem / remiſſione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> peccatoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / carnis reſurrectione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et vitam eterna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="eng" type="version">
                  <p>I Byleue in God the Father al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myghtye creatour of heuen &amp; earth. And in his onely ſone Ieſus Chryſte our lorde. Whiche was con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyued by the holy ghoſt / and borne of the virgyn Mary. which ſuffered vnder Ponce Pylate / and was cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyfyed and dyed / and was buryed.
<pb facs="tcp:11271:3"/>And deſcended in to the helles / and roſe agayne the thyrde day fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deth to lyfe. And aſcended in to the heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; ſytteth on the ryght hande of the father almyghty. And ſhal come a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gayne / &amp; iudge both quycke &amp; dead. I byleue in the holy ghoſt / and the holy chyrch catholyke / the holy com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>munyon of ſayntes / &amp; the remyſſion of ſynnes / &amp; the generall reſurreccyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the body &amp; ſoule / and euerlaſtyng lyfe. Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer_sequences">
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to ſyng</p>
               <div xml:lang="lat" type="Confiteor_sequence">
                  <p>Confitemini dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o quoniam bonus:</p>
                  <p>Quonia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ſeculu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> miſericordia eius</p>
                  <p>COnfiteor deo / beate Marie / omnibus ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ctis et vobis / quia peccaui nimis cogitatione locutione et opere mea culpa. Precor ſanctam Maria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / oe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſanctos dei et vos orare pro me. Miſereatur veſtri omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens deus / et dimittat vobis omnia
<pb facs="tcp:11271:3"/>peccata veſtra: liberet vos ob omni malo ſaluet et confirmet in bono et perducat vos ad vita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eterna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Amen</p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>diutorium noſtrum in nomine domini.</p>
                  <p>Qui fecit celum et terram.</p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>it nomen dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i benedictu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
                  <p>Ex hoc nunc &amp; vſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> in ſeculu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="Kyrie">
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yrye eleyſon</p>
                  <p>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>
                           <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>pe</abbr>
                        <expan>Christe</expan>
                     </choice> eleyſon.</p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yrye eleyſon.</p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="lat" type="gospel_sequence">
                  <p>¶ Se<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quentia ſancti euangelij ſecundum / Marcu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / Matheu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / Luca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / Iohanne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
                  <p>Gloria tibi dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e.</p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er omnia ſecula ſeculoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="lat" type="sequence_from_the_Canon_of_the_Mass">
                  <p>Dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s vobiſcu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
                  <p>Et cum ſpu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tuo.</p>
                  <p>Surſum corda.</p>
                  <p>Habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus ad dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>m.</p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ratias agamꝰ dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o deo noſtro.</p>
                  <p>Dignum et iuſtum eſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="lat" type="dismissal">
                  <p>Pax domini ſit ſemper vobiſcu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
                  <p>Et cum ſpiritu tuo.</p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ta miſſe eſt.</p>
                  <p>Deo gratias.</p>
                  <div xml:lang="lat" type="final_versicle_for_Requiem">
                     <p>Requieſca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in pace. Amen.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="grace_before_dinner">
               <head>¶ Grace to be fayd before dyner.</head>
               <p>BEnedicite. Dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. The eyes of euery thynge do loke vp / and
<pb facs="tcp:11271:4"/>they hope in the good lorde / &amp; thou gyueſt them theyr fode in tyme con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient. Thou openeſt thy hande &amp; doeſt replenyſſhe euery ſenſyble cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ature with thy benediccyon. Glory be to the father / to the ſone / &amp; to the holighoſt. As it was in the begyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nynge / &amp; as it is nowe &amp; euer ſhall be. Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Lorde haue mercy on vs.</p>
               <p>Chryſte haue mercy on vs. Lorde haue mercy on vs. Our father. &amp;c. And let vs not be ouerco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me by tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ptacyon. But delyuer vs from all euyll Amen. Nowe let vs all pray.</p>
               <p>Good lorde blyſſe vs &amp; all thy gyftꝭ which we ſhal receyue of the by thy bounteouſneſſe thorowe Chryſt our lorde Amen. O lorde commaunde thou to blyſſe. The kynge of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall glory make vs to be pertenars of the celeſtyall mele. Amen.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11271:4"/>
God is charite / &amp; he that dwelleth in charite dwelleth in god / and god dwelleth in hym. Let vs pray that god maye dwell in vs / and that we may dwell in hym. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="grace_after_dinner">
               <head>¶ <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>race afte<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yner<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </head>
               <p>The god of peace &amp; loue dwell awaye with vs. O Lorde haue mercy on vs. Thankes be to god. Good lorde let all thy workes gyue knowledge to the / and let thy holy ſayntes gyue blyſſynge to the. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lory be to the father. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e gyue thankes to the almyghty god for all thy vnyuerſall gyftes &amp; benefites / whiche lyueſt &amp; reygneſte as god thoroughout all the worlde of worldes Amen.</p>
               <p>O all ye nacyons laude ye the lorde And all ye people prayſe ye hym Bycauſe his mercye is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fyrmed on
<pb facs="tcp:11271:5"/>vs / and the trueth of our lorde doth remayne eternally. Glory be to &amp;c. Lorde haue mercy on vs. Chryſte haue mercy on vs. Lorde haue mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy on vs. Our father which art. &amp;c. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hryſte dyd dyſtrybute goodes / &amp; gaue it to the poore. His iuſtice abydeth in the worlde of worldes.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhall blyſſe our Lorde in euerye tyme. His prayſe be euermore in my mouthe. My ſoule ſhalbe pray ſed in our lorde. Let them that be gentyll heare / &amp; they ſhall therof be glad. Magnifye ye the lorde with me / &amp; let vs exalte his name within hym ſelfe. Blyſſed be the name of our lorde fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the begyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ynge. Now / and euer throughe out the worlde. Hayle Mary. Nowe let vs praye. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ouchſafe thou lorde god to gyue eternall lyfe vnto al people. doynge
<pb facs="tcp:11271:5"/>good to vs for thy holy name Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Let vs blyſſe our lorde. Tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kꝭ be to our lorde god. God graunt that the ſoules of all faythfull people de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted out of this worlde / by his mercy may reſt ineternal lyfe Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God preſerue his chyrch vnyuerſal And this chyrch of england ſpeciall And the ſupreme heed therof oure kynge. And graunt vs the blyſſe without endynge. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> dayes</head>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>Enedicite. Dominus. God grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that they that are pore in ſpiryte may fede and they ſhalbe ſatyfyed: they that ſeke hym / theyr hertes and myndes ſhal lyue in the worlde of worldes. Glory be to &amp;c. Lorde haue mercy on vs. &amp;c. Our father which art. Let vs pray &amp;c. Good lorde blyſſe vs. &amp;c. O lorde
<pb facs="tcp:11271:6"/>commaunde thou to blyſſe. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he eternall kynge of glory refreſſhe vs w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the meate of thy ſpirituall fode. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he grace of our lorde Ieſu chryſt the charyte of god / the communyon of the holye ghoſte / be euer with vs all Amen. Breake to the hungry thy breade. And brynge the nedy men and wanderyng men into thy houſe. When thou ſeeſt one bare couer hym / and dyſprayſe not thyne owne brothers body.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hus the almyghty lorde ſayeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="grace_after_dinner">
               <head>¶ Grace after dyner</head>
               <p>THe God of peaſe and of loue dwell alway with vs. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he mercyfull god gyuer of mercy hath made a memory of his meruels. He hathe gyuen meate to all them that drede hym. Glory be to the father. We gyue thankes to the &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <pb facs="tcp:11271:6"/>
            <div type="grace_before_dinner">
               <head>¶ <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> grace to be ſayd <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> dyner</head>
               <p>THe ryght hande of god blyſſe our meate now brought hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and to be brought hyther. In the name of the father / &amp; the ſone &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="preprandial_grace">
               <head>¶ <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>other grace to be ſayd be<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ore dyner or ſupper.</head>
               <p>BEnedicite. Dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. Good lorde for thy grace mekely we call. Bleſſe vs our meates &amp; drynkes all In the name of the father. &amp; cetera</p>
            </div>
            <div type="grace_after_dinner">
               <head>¶ A ſhorte grace after dyner.</head>
               <p>FOr this feeſt now let vs blys our lorde. Thankꝭ be to god Hayle Mary. &amp;c. Nowe let vs all pray &amp;c. Vouchſafe. &amp;c. Let vs all blyſſe our lorde. Thankꝭ be to god God graunt &amp;c. God preſerue. &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="postprandial_grace">
               <head>¶ <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nother grace to be ſayde after dyner or ſouper.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11271:7"/>
BLyſſed be our lorde which of his grace. Hath ſende vs our fode / good tyme / and ſpace.</p>
               <p>Lorde haue mercy on vs. Chryſte haue mercy. &amp;c. Thankes be to god. Laude and prayſe / honoure / and glory. Be to that lord that reygneth on hye. Whoſe great mercy is euer redy. To all them that for it call.</p>
               <p>Therfore laude be to hym eternall. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>owe blyſſed be the name of oure lorde. Nowe and euer thorowe out the worlde. Amen. God preſerue his chyrche vniuerſall. &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="grace_before_supper">
               <head>¶ Grace before ſouper.</head>
               <p>BEnedicite. Dominꝰ. He that gyueth all thynge / now ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tify our ſouper. In the name of. &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="grace_after_supper">
               <head>¶ Grace after ſouper.</head>
               <p>BEnedicite. Dominꝰ. Blyſſed is god in all his gyftes / and
<pb facs="tcp:11271:7"/>holy in all his workes. Let hym be our helpe in the name of god which hath made heuen and earth.</p>
               <p>Blyſſed be the name. &amp;c. Vouch. &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="grace">
               <head>¶ <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>fore dyner.</head>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>Enedicite. Dominus. This is the day whiche our Lorde made / let vs ioye and be glad in the ſame. Glorye be to the. &amp;c. Lorde haue mercy on vs &amp;c. And let vs not &amp;c. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>owe let vs. &amp;c. Good lorde &amp;c. O lorde. &amp;c. The kinge of. &amp;c. Caſt ye out clene the olde leuen that ye maye be newe dowgh as ye are the ſwete brede / for Chryſt our Eſter Lambe is offered for vs / therfore let vs fede in our lorde. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="grace_after_Easter_dinner">
               <head>¶ Grace after dyner at Eſter</head>
               <p>COnfeſſe your ſelfes to the god of heuen whiche gyueth fode to euery ſenſyble creature. O thou
<pb facs="tcp:11271:8"/>good lorde &amp;c. Thankes be to god O all ye nacyons laude ye the lorde Bycauſe his mercy is confirmed on vs &amp;c. Glory be to the father. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Chryſte / in thy reſurreccyon the heuens and the earth be glad.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ Let vs pray.</head>
               <p>GOod lorde infude the ſpiryte of thy charyte in vs / that by thy pite thou mayſt make vs agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to thoſe thynges whiche thou haſte made by thy holy paſcall Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes. By that ſame our lorde Ieſu Chryſt thy ſone which lyueth and reyneth with the as god in the vnite of the ſame holy ſpiryte by all the worlde of worldes. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Ten_Commandments">
               <head>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ten co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement</head>
               <l>Lord grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t me grace to honor the</l>
               <l>One god &amp; neuer to ſwere in vayne</l>
               <l>The holy day to be kepte by me</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11271:8"/>
My parentes to obey &amp; maynteyne</l>
               <l>By thought ne dede no man to kyll</l>
               <l>To robbe nor to ſteale no where</l>
               <l>Nor to do lechery in acte or wyll</l>
               <l>Be no lyer / nor falſe wytneſſe bere</l>
               <l>Nor to deſyre my neyghbours wyfe</l>
               <l>His landes / ſeruauntes / or catell</l>
               <l>Theſe x. preceptes lorde all my lyfe</l>
               <l>Grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t me grace I maye kepe well.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="corporal_works_of_mercy">
               <head>¶ <gap reason="illegible" extent="3 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of mercy bodily.</head>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od giue me grace the ſicke to viſit</l>
               <l>And giue them mete that be hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gry</l>
               <l>To them that thurſte drynke to fet</l>
               <l>And preſoners to redeme and bye</l>
               <l>To clothe the naked euermore redy</l>
               <l>To pore wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derers to giue lodging</l>
               <l>And to brynge the deed to buriyng.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="spiritual_works_of_mercy">
               <head>¶ <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he vij work<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of mercy ghoſtly</head>
               <l>God grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t I may good cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel giue</l>
               <l>And teche them that ygnoraunt be</l>
               <l>To conforte them that be penſyue</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11271:9"/>
And to correcte with charyte</l>
               <l>To ſuffer in all aduerſyte</l>
               <l>My neyghbors treſpas to forgyue</l>
               <l>And to pray for grace whyle I lyue</l>
            </div>
            <div type="seven_deadly_sins">
               <head>¶ The .vij. Capitall ſynnes.</head>
               <l>Good lorde graunt me pryde to for ſake</l>
               <l>And not to ſyn in couetous</l>
               <l>Nor ſlouth / but in good workes to wake</l>
               <l>Nor to be wrath nor furyous</l>
               <l>Nor dyſdaynous nor enuyous</l>
               <l>Nor for to ſynne in glotony</l>
               <l>Nor in no carnall Lechery.</l>
            </div>
            <trailer>Thus endeth the. A B C tranſla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted out of Laten to to Englyſſhe with other deuoute Prayers.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Imprynted at Londo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Paules Chyrche yarde at the ſygne of the maydens heed by thomas Petyt.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:11271:9"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
